In this video, we will be talking about
capacitors.
A capacitor is a device that is used to
store
electrical charge. In real life, it might
look
like this. It's a small thing with two
rods
or two plates covered by an insulator that
looks
like this, but in reality it is actually
two
plates. Now, unlike a battery which
produces
energy through chemical reactions, a
capacitor
stores energy instead.
And the plates are also not touching, and
between
these plates is an insulating material
called
a dielectric. It could be air, sometimes
it's
other things such as paper is used as a
good
dielectric, but basically that insulates
between
the plates, and since the plates are
separated
by an insulator, charges can't cross
directly
from one plate to the other.
But for now, we don't need to know that
much
about dielectrics, just know that it's
used
to preserve the charge stored on each
plate.
When one of these capacitors acts and
connects
on a battery, initially electrons are
pushed
from one plate and pulled off the other
plate.
So this plate would have a net positive
charge,
while this plate will pull electrons from
it.
And this creates a charge.
And even though electrons don't cross the
dielectric,
there's an electric field formed between
the
plates, and that electric field is where
energy is actually stored. The energy
stored
in a capacitor is equal to E equals Cv, or
Q equals Cv, where Q is the charge stored,
C
is the capacitance, and V is the voltage
across
the capacitor. The capacitance depends
mostly
on the dielectric. Basically, C equals
epsilon
naught times A over D, where A is the area
of
the plates, D is the distance between
them,
and E is the permittivity of free space,
so
it's a constant. Increasing the plate area
basically
increases the capacitance, so that's why
bigger
capacitors can store more charges.
However, how does a capacitor actually act
in
a circuit? Well, when first connected to
the
battery, there's obviously going to be no
net
charge, so current flows and charge starts
building
up. However, as a capacitor charges, the
voltage
across the capacitor increases until it
has
a maximum charge. And since it has a
maximum
charge now, there's no voltage left in the
series
circuit to actually push the electrons
away
from the first capacitor. So, after a
while,
there is not going to be a current.
So, what you'd have to know is, initially,
after
the circuit starts, the capacitor acts as
a
normal wire, or as a short circuit. So, a
capacitor
acts like a short circuit.
So, basically you could ignore the
capacitor
initially, it just acts like a wire.
However, as charge builds up, and the
voltage
increases between the capacitor, so after
a
while, or a period of time, there is not
going
to be a current passing through the
capacitor.
So, basically it acts like an open circuit
to
be a current.
So, initially, basically you can imagine
it
would just look something like this. But
after
a while, you can imagine that the circuit
looks
like this. And that's basically it.
The energy stored in an electric field is
given
by a different formula, but the two main
formulas
you have to know are these.
But the energy stored between the electric
field
is E equals one over two C V squared.
And this is the energy that is released by
the
capacitor when you discharge it.
Energy released through discharge.
So, ultimately, capacitors are things that
store
charges. At first, initially, in a
circuit,
it acts like a short circuit, or basically
just
a wire connecting. But over time, as
charges
build up, the current is going to decrease
until
ultimately there is no current going
through
it at all. The capacitance, or the energy
stored,
depends on the area and the distance.
It's inversely proportional to the
distance,
and it's directly proportional to the
area.
And, yeah, that's basically all you need
to
know about capacitors. Thank you for
watching!